<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-04T22:36:52-06:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Club Linguistics</title><subtitle>Community to promote various stories from various domains in various languages.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes on Probability</title><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/probability/statistics/2022/02/05/probtheory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Probability" /><published>2022-02-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/probability/statistics/2022/02/05/probtheory</id><author><name>Saurav Jadhav</name></author><category term="Probability" /><category term="Statistics" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Is ROC Curve?</title><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/machine%20learning/2020/12/26/roc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is ROC Curve?" /><published>2020-12-26T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/machine%20learning/2020/12/26/roc</id><author><name>Saurav Jadhav</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><summary type="html">Consider heart data which consist of 13 features such as age, sex, chol (cholesterol measurement). Our goal is to predict whether an individual has heart disease based on the above features, this is a binary classification problem. That is, with only two classes. Let us suppose we have 100 samples (a sample corresponds to patient information) amongst which 90 samples are positive (have a heart disease) so if you say that all patients (100 of them)have heart disease, you have correctly classified 90/100 samples. You didn’t even build the model and got an accuracy of 90%. But, if we look carefully we will see that the dataset is skewed. That is, number of positive samples is far more than the negative samples (patients without heart disease). So, it is not advisable to decide best model just on the basis of accuracy because, it does not represent the data completely. So, you might get high accuracy, but your model will probably not perform that well when it comes to real-world samples. Therefore, we need a more reliable evaluation metric and hence, ROC comes into the picture. Here we will use SVM (support vector machine) as model with different values of gamma (parameter) for comparison and with the help of ROC curve figure out which value of gamma gives us the optimal result (best model). Let’s see this in detail. Rather than predicting samples are positive or not, we predict the probability of having heart disease for each sample, and if this probability is greater than the threshold, we say the given patient has heart disease. So let’s say we select a threshold value of 0.1 therefore, if the probability is greater than 0.1 we say that particular patient has heart disease. Now as we vary the threshold it is obvious that prediction will also vary. For example, if the threshold is 0, we will predict every sample in the data is positive (since, probability is greater than equals to 0). Similarly, if we have a high threshold of say 0.9, even though the patient has heart disease it is possible that prediction will be ‘no heart disease’ which is very risky! So we have to choose a threshold in such a way that not only we must have good predictions but also balance the tradeoff. Now we give a summary. Table.1 shows the possible results when applying a classiﬁer to the data, this table is also known as confusion matrix. Now, let us define terms given in the table require to build ROC curve. True positive (TP): Given a patient’s information (age, sex… values), if your model predicts heart disease, and the patient actually has heart disease then, it is considered a true positive. True negative (TN): Given a patient’s information, if your model predicts no heart disease, and the patient actually has no heart disease then, it is considered a true negative. In simple words, if your model correctly predicts positive class, it is true positive, and if your model correctly predicts negative class, it is a true negative. False positive (FP): Given a patient’s information, if your model predicts heart disease, and the patient actually has no heart disease then, it is considered a false positive. False negative(FN): Given a patient’s information, if your model predicts no heart disease, and the patient actually has heart disease then, it is considered a false negative. In simple words, if your model incorrectly (or falsely) predicts positive class, it is a false positive. If your model incorrectly (or falsely) predicts negative class, it is a false negative. Now, TPR/Sensitivity is defined as: TP / P Where P = TP+FN TPR is ‘The fraction of patients with heart disease which are correctly identified’. FPR/False Positive Rate is defined as: FP / N FPR is ‘The fraction of patients without heart disease which are incorrectly identified as with heart disease’. Specificity is defined as: TN / N Where N = TN+FP Specificity is ‘The fraction of patients without heart disease which are correctly identified’. ROC provides a simple way to summarize the information related to different thresholds and resulting TPR and FPR values.Table.2 illustrates TPR and FPR values for different thresholds. You might wonder why some threshold values are negative? I will explain this later. Now, Rather than building different tables (like Table.1.) for different values of threshold, you can just look at ROC curve to decide what threshold to select. Most of the time, the top-left value on ROC curve should give you a quite good threshold, as illustrated in Fig.1, and the corresponding threshold value is highlighted in Table.2. Depend on how many false positive you are willing to accept, you decide optimal threshold. For example, if you don’t want to have too many false positives you should have a high threshold value. This will however, also give you a lot more false negatives. Observe the trade-off and select the best threshold, by decreasing the threshold value of TPR, FPR increases and specificity decreases. Similarly, when we increase the threshold TPR, FPR decreases but specificity increases. AUC makes it easy to compare one ROC curve to another, larger the area under the curve the better the model. In Fig.2.The AUC for SVM with gamma is equals to 0.001is 0.88, the AUC for SVM with gamma is equals to 0.0001 is 0.76, and the AUC for SVM with gamma is equals to 0.00001 is 0.75. We say SVM with gamma is equals to 0.001 is better model than others, since, 0.88 is close to maximum value of AUC that is one, AUC corresponds to SVM with gamma is equals to 0.001 is illustrated in Fig.1., we expect a classifier that performs no better than chance to have an AUC of 0.5, the no information classifier in Fig.2 (red line) predicts every patient as ’with heart disease’ independent of actual target (class). You can also compare other classification models like: Logistic Regression, KNN classifier with SVM. AUC is a widely used metric for binary classification tasks in the industry, and a metric everyone should know about. Note: In general we use probabilities for comparison with the threshold. In case of SVM, decision function values are computed and are compared with the threshold, and can take positive or negative values, which can be seen in Table.2. But the prediction is done in the same way: if function value greater than threshold we assign the sample to the positive class (patient predicted as, ‘with disease’), otherwise we assign the sample to negative class (patient predicted as, ‘without disease’). References: Approaching (Almost) Any Machine Learning Problem, book by Abhishek Thakur. An Introduction to Statistical Learning with Applications in R, book by Robert Tibshirani, Gareth James, Trevor Hastie, Daniela Witten.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/Fig_2_to_upload.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/Fig_2_to_upload.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Jack Bogle’s Timeless Investment Principles</title><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/investing/2020/10/10/jack-investing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jack Bogle’s Timeless Investment Principles" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/investing/2020/10/10/jack-investing</id><author><name>Saurav Jadhav</name></author><category term="Investing" /><summary type="html">Jack Bogle was the founder and chief executive of The Vanguard Group, one of the world’s largest investment companies and he is also regarded as the father of index funds. Below are the principles given by Jack in his book Common Sense on Mutual Funds.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/markus-spiske-investing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/markus-spiske-investing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What Is K-Means Clustering?</title><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/machine%20learning/2020/10/04/k_means.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is K-Means Clustering?" /><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/machine%20learning/2020/10/04/k_means</id><author><name>Saurav Jadhav</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><summary type="html">It refers to a very broad set of techniques for finding subgroups, or clusters in a data set. When we cluster the observations of a dataset we seek to partition them into distinct groups so that the observations within each group are quite similar to each other, while observations in different groups are quite different. An application of clustering arises in marketing. We may have access to a large number of measurements (example:median household income, occupation, distance from the nearest urban area, and so forth) for a large number of people. Our goal is to perform market segmentation by identifying subgroups of people who might be more receptive to a particular form of advertising, or more likely to purchase a particular product. The task of performing market segmentation amounts to clustering the people in the data set. In general, we can cluster observations on the basis of the features in order to identify subgroups among the observations, or we can cluster features on the basis of the observations in order to discover subgroups among the features. Since clustering is popular in many ﬁelds, there exist a great number of clustering methods. But, we will be specifically focusing on K-means clustering, where we seek to partition the observation into pre-specified number of clusters. K-means clustering is a simple and elegant approach for partitioning a data set into K distinct, non-overlapping clusters. By non-overlapping we mean that no observation belongs to more than one cluster. To perform K-means clustering, we must ﬁrst specify the desired number of clusters K; then the K-means algorithm will assign each observation to exactly one of the K clusters. Figure.1. shows the results obtained from performing K-means clustering on a simulated example consisting of 150 observations in two dimensions, using three diﬀerent values of K. The idea behind K-means clustering is that a good clustering is one for which the within-cluster variation is as small as possible. That is, the difference between the observations in the same cluster is as small as possible. Here the question arises: How to define within-cluster variation? There are many possible ways to deﬁne this concept, but by far the most common choice involves squared Euclidean distance, where we compute the sum of square of differences amongst the observations with in the cluster, which gives us magnitude of how close or how far the observations are from each other, now since our goal is to minimize this within cluster variation, this is in fact a very diﬃcult problem to solve precisely, since there are almost K to the power n ways to partition n observations into K clusters. This is a huge number unless K and n are tiny! Fortunately, a very simple algorithm can be shown to provide a local optimum. Algorithm: K-Means Clustering : Randomly assign a number, from 1 to K, to each of the observations. These serve as initial cluster assignments for the observations. Iterate (repeat) until the cluster assignments stop changing: a. For each of the K clusters, compute the cluster centroid. The kth cluster centroid is the vector of the p feature means (average) for the observations in the kth cluster. b. Assign each observation to the cluster whose centroid is closest (where closest is deﬁned using Euclidean distance). In step 2(a) we compute the mean of the observations within the cluster (cluster centroid). Here an observation is nothing but a vector of p features. Then in step 2(b) we compute distance between the observation to every cluster centroid and then assign the observation to the cluster for which the distance is minimum. This means that as the algorithm is run, the clustering obtained will continually improve until the result no longer changes. When the result no longer changes, a local optimum has been reached. Figure 2 shows the progression of the algorithm on the toy example from Figure 1. K-means clustering derives its name from the fact that in Step 2(a), the cluster centroids are computed as the mean of the observations assigned to each cluster. Because the K-means algorithm ﬁnds a local optimum (minimizing the within cluster variance) rather than a global, the results obtained will depend on the initial (random) cluster assignment of each observation in Step 1 of Algorithm. For this reason, it is important to run the algorithm multiple times from diﬀerent random initial conﬁgurations. Then one selects the best solution, that is, Sum of within cluster variances of all the clusters (objective) is smallest. Figure 3 shows the local optima obtained by running K-means clustering six times using six diﬀerent initial cluster assignments, using the toy data from Figure 1. In this case, the best clustering is the one with an objective value of 235.8(least). As we have seen, to perform K-means clustering, we must decide how many clusters we expect in the data. The problem of selecting K is far from simple, and we may not know in advance how many clusters to select. Therefore, it is one of the drawbacks of K-means clustering. The mathematics of how clustering is performed is too technical to be discussed here. Reference: An Introduction to Statistical Learning with Applications in R, book by Robert Tibshirani, Gareth James, Trevor Hastie and Daniela Witten.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/k_means_1.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/k_means_1.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Waste Is Future OR Not ? An effective way to treat plastic waste</title><link href="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/environment/social%20issues/chemistry/2020/09/29/plastic-waste.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waste Is Future OR Not ? An effective way to treat plastic waste" /><published>2020-09-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/environment/social%20issues/chemistry/2020/09/29/plastic-waste</id><author><name>Anup Gawande</name></author><category term="Environment" /><category term="Social Issues" /><category term="Chemistry" /><summary type="html">The rapid rate of increase in plastic has led to the creation of increasing amounts of waste and this in turn poses greater difficulties for disposal.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/erik-mclean-plastic-waste_orig.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://clublinguistics.github.io/blogs/images/erik-mclean-plastic-waste_orig.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>